THOMAS HUBERT: Hello, everyone!
I'm really, really
glad to be here and be
able to share a little
bit more about our work.
And I would, of course, like
to organize the organizers
for inviting me to be
part of this class.
All right.
So 3 and 1/2 years ago, I had
just finished two big projects.
One of them was AlphaCode,
the other one was AlphaTensor.
I'll tell you a little bit
more about those in the future.
But basically, during the
Christmas holidays in 2021,
I stumbled on this
talk from 2019
called The Future
of Mathematics,
and the talk is over an hour.
But the comments were
extremely positive.
One person was saying, this is
the best lecture and the best
YouTube video ever.
I've never watched
anything more enjoyable.
So, I was pretty intrigued.
And I press Play, and it started
a chain of ineluctable events
that basically takes me
here in front of you today.
So in this talk, rather than
focusing on the details,
I'd really like to
focus on the big ideas
that allowed us to
work on AlphaProof,
and why we believe it has
an integral role to play
in the future of mathematics.
I will basically talk
first about the rise
of formal mathematics
and what that
is, and then about our
experience in reinforcement
learning and the
lessons we took away,
and how these two things
meet with other proof.
So Galileo said,
quite a long time ago,
that the laws of
nature are written
in the language of mathematics.
It was an incredible
prediction or insight,
because we've made a lot
of progress since Galileo.
And indeed now, just a few
equations on a single page
can describe how the universe
works extremely precisely.
Also in a famous essay called
"The Unreasonable Effectiveness
of Mathematics."
Eugene Wigner argues that
mathematics, not only
have a descriptive power, but
they also have predictive power.
And one example he gives,
if I'm not mistaken,
is the development
of matrix algebra
and its use in
quantum mechanics.
Of course, once you can describe
and predict the natural world,
you can start to shape it.
And if you look around us
in the world we live in,
the civilization, the
culture, all the tech,
that makes our current world--
well, basically mathematics is
just at the core of everything.
And maybe I would also like
to argue that mathematics
is a root node to intelligence.
The root node is a
word that Dennis really
likes to talk about.
And basically, it means
that from that root
is going to blossom a whole
tree of possibilities.
And why could we argue that
is because mathematics use--
requires reasoning and planning,
generalization and abstraction,
knowledge and creativity, open
ended and unbounded complexity.
And over the years,
I also understood
that mathematics is not
just this application
of logical rules,
one after the other.
It's really a art.
And so it even requires
an eye for beauty.
And so I used a lot
of keywords here,
and that you'll see them
reappearing during my talk.
And I hope that will make
this a bit more concrete.
In summary, I've tried to
convey to you that mathematics
is a root node to understand
the natural world,
but it also might be a
root node for intelligence.
So I think it's worth really
thinking about mathematics
and see what can we do for that.
But before that,
I'd like to give you
a really super brief history of
formalization in mathematics,
because basically
mathematics hasn't always
looked the way it looks now.
About 500 years before
Christ, the Greeks
had a great revelation.
They understood the
importance of the concept
of mathematical proof
and in some sense,
can you really imagine?
It's like you find
something that will tell you
with certainty that you
have attained eternal truth
and you can discover more and
more truths of our universe.
It must have felt incredible.
And since then, proofs is
at the heart of mathematics.
And what constitutes
a proof, however,
has evolved over the millenniums
of mathematical history.
One of the first breakthroughs,
I'm sure, that you know
is with Euclid and his book
Elements that had definitions,
axioms and theorems.
And so that's really the start
of axiomatization that has
really been developed much more
in the early 20th century with
Hilbert Program that really
developed these to land on what
we have now.
And so that's
axiomatization on one side.
On the other side, like
mathematics, at the beginning
it didn't really use symbols.
And that's for a very long time.
Even if the Greeks had
taken find axiomatization
and started to use some
symbols, the rest of the world
describe really mathematics
with a lot of words.
And so here you have
a square and 10 times
its root is equal to 39.
So today we would write this as
x squared plus 10x equals 39.
But look at this description of
how do you solve these things.
Take the coefficient of the
root, divide it into two parts
and multiply one
of them by itself,
add these to 39,
cetera, et cetera.
Now, you just write
this concise formula.
And there are two things
here that comes, it's first,
replacing--
using special-- in the
machine learning lingo,
using special
tokens for numbers.
We represent-- the digits
have special characters.
But also even more important--
I don't know which
one is more important,
but that helps with also--
I think only in
the 17th century,
René Descartes comes up with the
idea of using the early letter
of the alphabet to denote
constants and the end
of the letter--
of the alphabet x, y,
z to describe unknowns.
And so that's basically how
you end up with this formula.
But it takes--
I don't know how many-- it takes
until the 17th century to really
come up with those notations.
And I think it's
not hard to argue
that precise notation and
axiomatization really eliminated
ambiguities and logical error,
that symbolic notation made
complex manipulations
more tractable
and requires much
less cognitive load.
It also packs information
extremely densely
in terms of notation.
I can't remember exactly who
said that and if it was a joke
or not, but someone was
arguing that maybe the Einstein
notations was his
biggest contribution.
That might be pushing
it a little bit
with given the impact of general
relativity, special relativity,
and even his work to
introduce quantum mechanics.
But certainly, Einstein
notations are very important.
Actually, if you read
machine learning code,
you'll see that
appearing a lot as well.
But basically, once
you have those symbols
and you can lift yourself
up from particular examples,
you start to be able to observe
different common patterns
across different contexts.
And so that's where abstraction
and generalization comes up,
you can unify disparate
areas of mathematics.
And actually, you can
even create new fields.
And so my favorite
example here is really
the people who are
looking at the 5
axioms of Euclidean geometry.
And actually, I don't know,
for thousands of years,
I think, trying to see if they
could remove the fifth axiom.
And that actually led to
non-Euclidean geometry.
And in particular
Riemannian geometry,
which in this theme
of general relativity
was essential to get
general relativity.
So this formalization has
helped mathematics, but also
the other sciences,
in particular physics.
And so I would like to argue
that basically computer
formalization, which basically
means writing mathematics
in code, is just the next
logical phase in this grand arc
of mathematical formalism.
So there's been
quite a few languages
to describe mathematical
reasoning, such as coq
and Isabellle, and Lean is
one of the most recent ones.
Originally developed, I believe,
for software verification,
but also with
mathematics in mind.
And mathematicians saw
in Lean the tool that
would make the next big step
in mathematical formalism.
So it's a programming language.
It's a theorem prover and
interactive proof assistant.
And Lean has a really
vibrant open-source community
of mathematicians,
and it's been used
to formalize like cutting-edge
mathematics, fields medal
mathematics.
And then mathematicians
are on a huge quest
to basically build the
math library of the future.
So let me go there.
It's called Mathlib.
It's built open source.
And basically, the free
time of mathematicians.
And it has two big goals.
It aims to be
general and unified.
So general, it means that it
has the weakest assumptions
and the strongest results.
And unified is that it only
has one definition per concept.
So I was actually
pretty surprised
when I learned about
this unification idea,
because I thought
that mathematics
was written in a very
structured way already.
But apparently, it turns out
that, like for a given concept,
you may have several
papers that basically
talk about the same
concept, but they define it
in a different way.
That is not necessarily
compatible with each other.
And so you need to do
quite a bit of work
to actually try to find the
unifying definition that
underlies all those ideas.
And so that's actually
what takes the most
time in building mastery.
Maybe you can see,
in the presentation
I gave here that it's one
monolithic library, where
everything is
connected together.
And so this is very
important for modern math
because basically, modern
math is about trying
to connect all areas of math.
And there's been
observations that
actually like ideas from here
can help ideas from there.
And for instance, maybe
Fermat's Last Theorem proof
is a great example of this,
connecting two different areas
to try to prove
one huge theorem.
Now, there is also something
called the Langlands Program
that really explicitly
tries to do that and connect
all these areas.
So it's really
important that you
have a library that
basically can connect
all different areas of maths.
Currently, the library
covers about 80%
of the undergrad curriculum, and
most of the library, however,
is above the undergraduate.
So it has a lot of
irregular coverage.
And because-- I think
particular examples are
complex analysis or PDE theory.
OK.
All right.
But why do all of this?
Is because computer
formalization
unlocks enormous synergies.
And maybe to explain myself a
little bit, I have to step back.
And for those of you who are
coders, maybe just understanding
the right code and be able to
use all the software stack,
that should be already a
huge win for mathematics.
But basically,
the other property
of when you write
mathematics in code
with those languages,
such as Lean,
is that you get
perfect verification.
So when you write a proof and
you write the correct proof,
Lean is going to tell
you, yes, this is correct.
And when you've
made a mistake, Lean
is going to tell you this
is-- your proof is not correct
or it's still incomplete.
So from these two things,
you get some instant wins.
First, your correctness
concerns completely disappear.
You can trust giant
proofs and you
can delegate proof checking
entirely to the computer.
And so I think it's
important to note
that it's my understanding
that it's not
like all areas of mathematics
are suffering from concerns
about correctness.
I think in reality,
most maybe areas,
where mathematicians feel pretty
comfortable about their ability
to discern correctness
from mistakes.
But I've been hearing that in
maybe some of the areas that
are more abstract
areas, actually,
they start to be real
concerns for correctness.
So that's not everywhere, but
that starts to be important.
So these are the instant wins.
But those perfect verification
and software stack
has really a
knock-on effect that
could lead to game changers.
So first, I think for all
of you who are coders,
to bring all the tools that
we have developed for coding
should already be
a big, big win.
Next, it have transformed
mathematics into a video game.
So what does this
video game look like?
Well, you have what
are the levels?
The levels are the
different theorems.
And then you can
interact in those levels.
And basically, Lean will
tell you, yes, you've
completed the level or not
with this perfect verification
feedback.
You always have harder level.
And maybe contrary to
other games, where--
I don't know, you have
to shoot other people.
This is a super meaningful,
useful and profound game.
You are basically adding
new truths for eternity.
And the Lean people
describe this
as they could do
this 14 hours a day
and they are constantly getting
positive reinforcements.
This also means that it's great
for education because like a lot
younger people now are really
used to using computers
and softwares.
And it's great because
it's interactive, right?
when it's fun,
it's easy to learn.
And you can also
create software,
such that the detail of--
the level of detail is
adapted to the person who
is reading rather than the level
that the author thought was
interesting.
I don't know if you read
a lot of maths papers
or you look at solutions
of some problems
you are trying to solve.
Sometimes people say this, well,
this next step is quite obvious,
but maybe it is
not for you and you
would love to see more detail.
I have also an example
from-- actually from my dad,
who recently tried to
learn Galois theory
in a different online
class, and so he
went through week 1 and
week 2 and week 3, all good.
But then when he was
going through week 4
and trying to do
the homework, he
realized that there was
something he didn't understand.
And he basically needed
someone to explain to him.
And he messaged the professor,
but unfortunately, the professor
didn't reply.
And so he was basically
completely stuck.
But imagine that instead
he was doing this in Lean,
then Lean would
have said exactly
what is right, what is wrong,
what is missing, et cetera.
And he would be able to have
constant feedback without having
to ask his teacher.
Now, I want to go
to the last point.
It's actually a point that
has been made by Terry Tao,
I think, about a year
and a half ago, at least.
And he describes that basically
using computer formalization
will unlock massive
collaboration
between mathematicians.
And so why does he say that?
Well, apparently
the current state
of mathematics collaboration
is that you can do--
most of the papers are either
single-author or two-author
papers and the max is
really five-author papers.
And the reason why is
because every author needs
to check everyone else's work.
And so basically, having
more and more collaborators
doesn't really scale
because you still need
to check everyone else's work.
And so that's where computer
formalization and [? password ?]
verification comes in, is that
if you could trust the computer
to check the proofs,
then suddenly you can--
it opens up working on
mathematical projects to, I
don't know, thousands of people
because you could have someone
you've never met, who lives
in the middle of nowhere,
who contributes a little bit to
your proof of [? Lean ?] there.
And then Lean will say,
yes, this is correct.
And then you can
just move on, right?
And so there's been
maybe-- there's
been a few projects like this.
I think Mathlib is maybe one
of the coolest demonstrations,
where you have hundreds of
mathematicians working together
to build this library
of the future.
But I think Terry
Tao is also arguing
that you could use that
to do new mathematics,
and has actually
launched a project
in the past called
Universal Algebra, where
he was exploring that.
But basically, I think
in ML, at the moment,
we are all about scaling.
And here basically,
you could scale
humans to do mathematics
and potentially
maybe tackle harder problems.
All right.
So should everyone go to
computer formalization?
It's awesome.
The reality is that there
are still challenges
for computer formalization.
In my estimates, about only
0.1% to 1% of mathematicians
have adopted Lean.
It's a small community of
mathematicians, a vibrant one.
But why is that? is because it's
actually not yet a great tool
for mainstream research.
Like, a lot of
programming languages,
it has a steep learning
curve, and it also
requires a significant
time investment
because to get
perfect verification,
you need to be able to
write every single detail.
And so that takes
a lot more time.
Maybe that's not the place
where you want to focus.
You want to focus on the things
you don't yet know how to solve,
not on the things that
are more obvious to you.
And so that will be improved.
And the tooling and
the library matures.
But at the moment, there's
still some things missing.
And obviously, there
is also a massive lack
of necessity for research.
But I'm hoping
that the arguments
I've outlined in
the slide before
are going to change a
little bit at that point.
So now I just want to show you
a little bit what it looks like.
So this is a proof that
you may know about.
It's called-- it's
about how many-- it's
about proving that there is
an infinite number of primes.
And OK, so this is what
it looks like in Lean.
I hope you can see,
that it's big enough.
And so-- oops, OK.
Here it is.
This is the theorem statement.
And I think what
is remarkable is
that because you
can use Lean code,
this looks pretty much what
you would write yourself
on a piece of paper.
It says that for all n natural
numbers, there exists p,
such that p is bigger
than n and p is prime.
So that's how-- one way
to say that there is
an infinite number of primes.
This is what the
proof looks like.
So fairly compact in this case.
And the fact that you can
understand all of this
is because, basically Lean is a
language-based high level syntax
mirroring normal mathematics.
So let me go a
little bit on what
it looks like to
interact with this thing.
So here is the first
line of the proof.
And this is actually
the main insight
that Euclid had is to consider
first n factorial plus 1
and the mean fact of it.
So what is the mean fact?
Is the mean factor of
n factorial plus 1.
And so I want to
draw your attention
on the box on the right there
called the Tactic state.
And so basically, that's
what Lean returns to you.
It says, oh, here are
the things we know.
And here are the things
we still need to prove.
So we know that n
is a natural number.
We know that p is this mean
factor of n factorial plus 1.
And you still need to show
that there exists a p,
such that p is bigger
than n and p is prime.
So let's go second line.
Second line says, oh, let's
prove that n factorial plus 1
is not one.
And you have actually the proof
in line with maybe a few more
characters than you really want
to prove something this easy.
But on the right,
you see that you
have a new fact in your arsenal
is that n factorial plus 1
is not one.
And then we are going to say,
now let's prove that p is prime.
And the proof you say, well,
it's because it's basically we
took the minimum factor.
The minimum factor
is obvious that it's
a prime unless the thing
you've taken up is one.
And so that's why
you have this thing
you needed to prove before.
And then the proof continues.
And at the end, you should see
in your Tactic state no goals.
And it used to be, I think
in a previous version of Lean
that you'd also received
this ta-da emoticon.
And I think
unfortunately, it's been
removed from the
current version of Lean.
But basically, it's
your little reward
for completing this level.
So just to recap;
computer formalization.
There is a really
vibrant community that
has a huge enthusiasm for this.
They are building the library
of the future in their own time.
It has many, many
ways in which it
can unlock enormous synergies,
but it still has some way to go.
And this community
and myself as well,
we have the belief that
this will inevitably
play an integral role in
the future of mathematics.
Just this work pushed the
computer formalization.
All right.
So now I want to talk about some
concurrent development in AI
and focus on something
that was extremely
popular a few years ago.
Got forgotten a bit in
the last couple of years.
And now that is making
a comeback big time.
So hopefully, like you've
picked up on my hints
with this little reward
and this environment,
this interactiveness,
this is video game.
I want to talk about
reinforcement learning.
So what is reinforcement
learning also known as RL?
Basically it's just
trial and error learning.
It's a very, very
general framework
of an agent trying
to achieve a goal.
So really, this agent learns by
interacting with an environment
to maximize the reward.
And I think there is sometimes a
misconception about this reward
that has to be very
dense or it has
to guide you towards
the solution, et cetera.
Not at all-- in the
framework of RL,
the reward can be basically
have I achieved my goal or not?
So basically, in RL, we
really need to have a goal.
But then your reward can be
goal achieved equal than 1,
otherwise 0 all the time.
If you don't really have a goal
that you want to try to achieve,
then maybe that doesn't fit very
well into the DRF framework.
But if you have a go, then
super framework to work with,
especially since it has
actually been proven
to work really, really well.
So here is a sample of the most
successful stories coming out
of DeepMind when RL was
basically run at scale.
So as you can see,
there are a lot
of examples of games
and video games.
So for instance, the seminal
work on Atari, the work on go
and StarCraft and Stratego.
But as I said, RL is
not confined to games.
It's about trying
to achieve a goal.
And so here, like
on the bottom row,
there is AlphaDev
and AlphaTensor,
which were used to
discover new algorithms.
And the bottom on the
right is basically
RL was used to try to
control in a token [? mac ?]
the shape of the plasma to get
better nuclear fusion reactions.
So you can see, it is
a very general setup.
Now, I had myself the
luck to spend my days
on AlphaGo and its descendants.
And this is what I
call the Zero Series.
And especially from
AlphaGoZero, we
showed that we could train
an agent to master domains.
And when I say
master, I actually
mean, being the world
champion, hands down
at the time when
those things came out.
And we learned to do that
without any human input
information, or we basically
learned everything from scratch.
And so I want to talk to you
about the Zero philosophy, which
I think is a great
philosophy for research.
And it's about this.
If an agent can learn to
master an environment,
tabula rasa, so without
any information,
then basically
you've demonstrably
shown that you
have a system that
is able to discover and learn
new knowledge by itself.
And it also means that this
algorithm is general and should
apply to other domains.
And I think the ability of being
able to discover new knowledge.
This is particularly
important to advance science,
because a big part
of doing science
is to just explore areas that
are not yet well understood
and advance knowledge.
And you need to accumulate
knowledge, continuously
generate and discover
new, interesting truths.
And that's a huge
part of doing science.
So especially, for research, I
think this is like a great way
to demonstrate that you
can discover new things.
I would say that, especially now
with the big success of LLMs,
maybe a more pragmatic
point of view
is to be able to start at
a certain knowledge base,
and then you want to know
that your algorithm is
going to continue to discover
new things from there.
So you don't really
need to start from 0.
What you really need is to
have this algorithm that
can discover new things.
And we've demonstrated
that you can do this
with this research and
these AlphaZero [INAUDIBLE].
So let me go into some examples.
AlphaGoZero and AlphaZero.
As I said, they learned simply
by playing against themselves,
starting completely
from random playing.
And what we observed
is that they basically
rediscovered human
patterns, accumulating
thousands of years
of human knowledge,
maybe in a matter of days.
But ultimately, some
of those patterns
were discarded in preference
of new discoveries
that humans don't
even know about,
they don't even know about.
So in Go, I believe that,
AlphaGo basically starting
a new move at move--
I would say move 5, a move that
wasn't even played by humans.
And I've heard, if
I'm not mistaken,
that Magnus Carlsen was saying
that because his coach was
really good at
using engines and he
got to use AlphaZero like
engines when those came out.
He got a big advantage
momentarily over the other chess
players, because basically
these things were playing
very differently and
people were not used to it
and they didn't know how to
handle those new situations.
So that's Go and chess.
And actually, if you look
at, for instance, the figure
I showed on the
bottom right, and this
is trying to show the
frequency of AlphaZero
playing that particular
pattern called,
for instance, the
Caro-Kann defense.
And you can see that, it
basically discovers it
after two hours of training.
It plays it for about four
hours quite consistently.
And then this pattern
starts to disappear
from the games
AlphaZero is playing,
probably because it has found a
way that makes this pattern not
very interesting anymore.
While on the bottom,
the Queen's gambit
seems-- the frequency at which
the Queen's gambit is played
is just increasing over
time-- over training time.
All right.
Now, let me talk
about Alpha Tensor.
And so this was a
work that was trying
to find what is the best way to
multiply two matrices together.
And so maybe the naive algorithm
that you may have learned
at school requires n cube
operations when you are trying
to multiply 2n by n matrices.
So for 2 by 2 matrices, you
need eight multiplications,
for 4x4 multiplications,
you need 64 multiplications,
et cetera, et cetera.
And so there was at some
point a big discovery
from a person named
Strassen that found that
for 2 by 2 matrices,
actually you
could do it with only
seven multiplications.
And he also showed
that this was optimal.
You couldn't do
better than that.
But as soon as we went to
4x4 matrices, basically,
we knew nothing more than
applying Strassen algorithm
twice.
And so you still reduces from
64 to 49 multiplications.
And so in AlphaTensor, we try
to discover a new efficient
and provably correct algorithm
for basically tasks that look
like matrix multiplication.
And it actually did.
It found a new things in
actually many different sizes,
discovering brand new knowledge
that humans never known about.
And so if you had only trained
on what humans had known,
then you would have
never discovered those.
As a big bonus, as
part of this work,
we show that basically
we could basically--
AlphaZero could tackle
huge action spaces.
So as I wrote here,
10 to the power 30.
But basically for practical
purposes, this is just infinite.
And so all those
successes Go, Chess,
Tensor decomposition are all
specific to a certain task
if you want a certain level,
but under the hood is basically
the same AlphaZero algorithm
that is running and making
those discoveries.
And so what we had
in mind is like,
is there an environment
that captures
a much broader class of tasks
that are relevant for science?
And you guessed it, our answer
is yes, it's mathematics.
But just before we
get there, the lessons
we've learned from
all this work.
So what made those
systems superhuman?
I've listed up what I
believe are the four
most important properties.
First is to scale
up trial and error.
And basically to
discover new knowledge,
you need to try
something new and be
able to learn based on
the feedback you receive.
And if your feedback
is not grounded,
if you invent your own
feedback, then it's really--
I think it's really hard once
you venture out of what's known.
And so you really
need a way to measure
if you're achieving
your goals or not,
where you are in the world--
where are you in your solution,
et cetera, et cetera.
And also AlphaZero
uses a lot of search,
and I believe-- it's my
belief that search can really
accelerate the discovery
of new paths and skills.
And it's because
most of the time when
you sample a different
action, not the action that
has the highest probability.
If you try that action, most of
the time it's going to be bad,
but sometimes it's
going to be good.
And you need to discover
why that action might
be good or not.
And so you need to
follow up on playing well
after you play that action.
And I think for instance,
AlphaGo and Move 37
is a good example of that.
It had a very low
probability of being played,
but it was still
explored in the search.
And then it was discovered
that was a really good move.
And so it became--
it was played and
it was described
as being very creative.
And the final one is you need
to have a good curriculum
to take you all the
way to superhuman.
And in the AlphaZero case,
in Go and Chess and Shogi,
we relied on the fact that
it was a two-player game.
And so you could do self-play.
You basically always have the
right opponent to play against,
and that was really important.
So now let me try to
connect those two.
Scaled up trial and
error; we have--
Lean is the environment to
explore mathematics completely
in silico.
And the algorithm is going
to come from AlphaZero.
And again, Lean is going to
give us this grounded feedback
signal.
It's going to tell us,
what have we proved so far,
what's left to be proved.
And it's going to tell
us when we are done,
when we get a correct proof.
For such, we can rely on
AlphaZero's search algorithm.
It works pretty well.
And maybe the question
mark is what do we
do with the curriculum?
And in some sense, where
are the levels coming from?
So you've understood kind
of the idea of AlphaProof
is to use Alpha
Zero for mathematics
and in particular,
formal mathematics.
So, let me make a napkin
master plan for AlphaProof.
So Lean gives us a way to
scale up trial and error,
with an environment to
explore mathematics completely
in silico, and a perfect
feedback signal for proving.
And then now, if we
extrapolate from the work
we've done in the
other domains, and I
conclude, we can therefore
reach superhuman intelligence
and discover new truths,
just like in Go, chess,
Tensor decomposition provided we
can generate high enough quality
and quantity of
problems and RL works.
So I'm very bullish on RL works.
And so as I said, the
question that remains
is how can we generate high
enough quality and quantity
of problems?
Where do the problems come from?
And so I think one
of the answer has
to be that the problems
partly comes from the humans.
And maybe the most
important reason
why is that it's because we
want to help human mathematics.
We could try to create
alien mathematics.
But really, what we would like
is to help human mathematics
and contribute in
that community.
And maybe a more
pragmatic reason
is that humans have
already come up
with a lot of problems
that are quite interesting.
But of course, we
should not throw away
the second part,
where AlphaProof
was defined the problem.
And so I think there is
maybe two ways to slice this.
One is AlphaProof
defines a problem
around human mathematics.
And we've done a
little bit of that
already with auto
formalization and test-time RL.
So it's perfectly
fine if you don't
understand what I mean here.
And I'll try to explain
those a bit later.
But the other part is
basically really augmenting
human mathematics.
So ideally, AlphaProof
would be able to discover
new areas of mathematics,
build new theories, et cetera,
that humans find interesting.
And yes, so these
are maybe where
the problems can come from.
So before we move on, I
want to take a step back
because if we're thinking
about AI for mathematics,
there is potentially a choice.
There is a choice of doing
it in natural language
or in formal language.
So I've been arguing a long
time now for the formal part.
But actually, most effort
in AI, at the moment,
is on informal mathematics or
doing basically mathematics
in natural language.
And the reason why is
because basically all
of the data of mathematics,
by many orders of magnitude
is written in natural
language, of course.
So you have this massive
library that is growing
and that contains
quite a lot of maths,
but it's still a few
orders of magnitude
smaller than the
amount of mathematics
you can find in textbooks, in
an archive and published papers,
et cetera, that are all
written using natural language.
So that's the trade
off you get when
you use formal mathematics
is you really have
a very small amount of data.
That's when again, you
bump into the question
of how do you get the problems,
where the problems come from.
And however, I guess,
it's my opinion
that because natural
language mathematics at least
the reasoning part
is not verifiable.
And I believe that this is
an issue if you're-- really
your goal is to build a system
that can go beyond human
knowledge and create
new knowledge.
And you can, of course,
improve the reliability
of those systems.
But the problem in
mathematics is really
that if you build on
any false statement,
then it destroys everything
you do afterwards.
So you really need
like 100% reliability.
And that's a property
of mathematics.
And that's why I think that
verifiability is very important.
And basically, Lean is already
superhuman at verification.
And I say all of
this for mathematics,
but actually I believe this
is true for many important,
impactful applications
that we cannot solve yet.
And the scientific
problems, in particular.
So in the domains,
we cannot solve--
there is almost
by construction--
there is not much data
available because the domain is
relatively poorly understood.
And maybe it could even
be a completely new domain
that has just been discovered.
You could also have applications
that are somewhat niche.
And maybe if you think
about what AGI would do,
you could argue that maybe
mathematics is a bit niche,
but it's still
extremely impactful.
And it's conceivable
that generalization
from all the other data
would be somewhat limited.
And so if we had data
scarce, we really
need a process that
can continuously
generate and discover new
interesting facts that are not
yet represented in the data.
And you need a way to
grant those new facts
so that you can check
that you are basically
constantly adding new truths
and building on top of neutrals.
And so this is really
a [? AlphaProof ?]
foundational bet is that
perfect verification will,
in the long run, be the
most important property
for mathematics.
So let me recap.
RL meets formal math.
So we have a proven recipe
to build an agent that
can discover new
knowledge by themselves
and reach superhuman
intelligence in certain domains.
And the key ingredients--
I have highlighted are
scaled up, trial and error
and grounded feedback.
And basically, formal
math provides us
with those key ingredients.
So these are the big ideas
that behind [INAUDIBLE].
So now let me talk to you
a little bit about the IMO
and our participation in 2024.
So first, what's the IMO?
The IMO stands for the
International Mathematics
Olympiad.
It's basically the
world-championship level event
in mathematics that brings
together the best young minds
from around the world.
So every country brings their
top-six high school students,
and they try to solve 6 problems
in two sessions of 4.5 hours.
So basically in total, they have
nine hours to solve 6 problems.
And in these six problems,
there are two easy problems,
two medium problems
and two hard problems.
So let me first
try to illustrate
what it means to take
the top-six high school
students for the USA.
So let's say there is about 17
million high-school students.
It's not like every kid
loves maths and is going
to do a maths competition.
They might instead
play video games
and maybe in the
future actually build
a maths library of the future.
But anyways, at the moment,
there is about 60,000 of them
that participate in
these AMC competitions.
If they do well and they
are still into this,
they might go and participate
in this AMC competition.
And so for those of you
who have been following
the benchmarks
used in AI, you may
know about this
math benchmark that
basically contains a lot of
AMC and [? AIME ?] problems.
And so the reason why is
that, basically, AI need--
what you need to do in
the [? AIME ?] is to--
the solution is always an
integer between 1 and 1,000.
And so it makes it easy to
check whether your system has
outputted the correct
answer or not.
Like, the correct number.
You can check that
very easily and use
that as a grounded feedback.
The problem is it
doesn't tell you
whether your reasoning to
get there is correct or not.
Now, if you need to
get 177, then I still
believe that it's indeed--
it's more likely that you
have correct reasoning when you
come up with the right answer.
And so that might still help
to improve the reasoning.
And basically, what's
happening is improving
the reasoning of those models.
But anyway, when you do
really well at the [? AIME, ?]
you may participate in
the USA Maths Olympiad.
There's only 250 now.
Then if you are
in the top there,
you may go to the IMO
camp and from there
only the top six
people are selected.
So you can see there is
basically six or seven orders
of selection.
And I'm told by my colleague
who did the IMO from--
for the UK that they
study for 1,000 of hours,
maybe an average of three
hours for three years.
So really intense training
for this competition.
Now, let me share a little
bit about the problems.
And I'll start with this
quote from Po-Shen Loh.
The Po-Shen Loh is not anyone.
He's not new to the IMO.
He was actually the
coach, the national coach
for USA for the last 10 years.
And he said, "I tried this
year's problems while at the IMO
and it took me hours and context
about the IMO problems are
specifically selected
to be non-standard."
"So during the IMO
itself, national coaches
meet to pick the problems
to appear on the exam.
One of the most important
tasks of that group
is to avoid problems
similar to problems
that appear anywhere before.
And so they go through a
great lengths to ensure this."
And so that's why basically
we really wanted to--
we picked the IMO
as a goal for us
is because we thought there
was really a test of reasoning
and not of knowledge.
And as Po-Shen Loh says,
even for specialists,
even for the national
coach of the USA
has been doing
this for 10 years,
it would take him hours
to solve those problems.
And the final property of
participating at the 2024 IMO
was that those problems--
those problems were not leaked.
And so you really need
it to be able to reason
to solve those problems.
And as I said, they are easy,
medium, and hard problems.
Easy is in fact, those
problems are not easy
at all because only
half of the participants
solve two or more problems.
And so you take the top six from
each country and half of those
won't be able to solve
the easy problem.
All right.
So now, let's go really
to this IMO 2024.
And I'd like to relive
a part of it with you.
So we had contacted
the IMO organization,
and we had agreed with them that
they will send us the problems.
We had contacted some judges,
also part of the competition,
so they could grade
our solutions.
And we try to participate.
So I just want to make sure I
clarify exactly what our IMO
participation was.
And I think a good
way to think about it
is more like an Apollo program.
And so what we really
wanted to know is,
can we actually reach the moon?
Can our solar system solve
the 2024 IMO problem at all?
And given the
computer that Google
can give us at that time and
enough time for doing reasoning.
So it was really
about this like,
can we build a system that can
solve those problems at all?
And I think at the time
when we got started,
it was believed that this was
like five or 10 years away.
So now let me take you to seven
months before January 2024.
So we are seven
months away, and we
need to make a decision
about geometry.
So why geometry?
Is because Mathlib is very
sparse in 2D Euclidean geometry,
doesn't have much of what you
need to know about Euclidean
geometry, mostly because
researchers don't really care
about 2D Euclidean geometry
that is useful for the IMO.
And so we're a bit
unsure what to do.
We are debating whether
maybe we actually
don't do geometry
at all or we try
to fill in that part in
Mathlib so that our agent has
the basic knowledge that is
expected every student to have.
And so we are debating
this when miraculously,
another group within
Google DeepMind
turned out to have been working
on exactly the IMO geometry
problem.
And they already have a system
that is very, very strong.
Their system was
already approaching
gold-level medal performance
on the geometric problems.
We learned about that because
they published a paper in Nature
in early January 2024.
So miracle.
But we decided to join
forces with them for July.
And so AlphaGeometry
will tackle geometry
and AlphaProof will tackle
algebra, number theory
and combinatorics.
A couple of months later, we
are debating another thing.
So we've been training
AlphaProof on proving theorems.
But not all questions are
on the form prove that.
And actually some require
an answer to be determined.
Like, find all x such that.
And this is not just an
integer like the [? AIME, ?]
It could be-- it's the
set of these numbers that
have this property, et cetera.
And so this actually
not obvious how
to do well in formal
language because you have
these tautological case where
it says, well, what are all
the x such that property
p holds and says,
what is- if the set of
numbers where p holds?
And you have a really
easy time to prove that.
But that's definitely not
what the judges were after.
And so actually,
the answer itself
is a bit of a subjective thing.
And we debate what
we should do is
we do what's known
outside as the easy mode.
We basically feed in the
correct answer to AlphaProof,
and we ask AlphaProof
to prove it.
Or we go with hard
mode, where we
try to determine the answer we
have-- something that determines
the answer and we prove it.
I personally don't really
like easy and hard keywords
here because it's
fairly well known
that the bit that is the hardest
for the IMO is the proving part.
It's not really to
guess the answer.
But anyway, so we are debating.
We are not sure
exactly what to do,
but after thinking
about it through,
it's pretty clear that
we need to do hard mode.
And what's cool is that
actually guessing the answer
is exactly what Gemini
has been trained on.
And so we decided that we will
generate candidates ourselves
with Gemini, and we will
attempt to prove and disprove
all possible candidates
without proof.
So that's how we're
going to participate.
Now, the final thing
we are debating about
is about the input that
the system should receive.
So it will receive the
natural language description
of the problem, for
instance, in English--
actually, if you
participate at the IMO,
you can choose the
language in which
you will receive the problems.
You're-- not everyone has
to read it in English.
You can have it in Russian
or in Chinese or in Japanese.
You can choose
your own language.
Unfortunately, they don't
propose Lean as a language.
And so we are debating
whether we will send English
to the system or we'll
ask our experts internally
to manually
formalize the problem
and send that as an
input to the system.
And so we debate this a
little bit with our judges.
And very quickly, we
have the same opinion
because what we
really care about is
the mathematical reasoning and
problem solving at the IMO.
And that's what
we are there for,
not really about our
capabilities or actually
translating the problem
in formal language.
And so we decide that it's OK
for what we want to achieve,
that we will give the
formalized problems as input.
And so we ask our experts
to manually formalize
the problems for the system.
So if I recap.
Our protocol is going to
look something like this.
So we are going to officially
receive the problems at 1:00 PM.
the Lean experts will first
manually formalize the problems.
And then that's where the--
after that the AI comes in.
So we'll generate hundreds of
answer candidates with Gemini.
AlphaProof will try to filter
all the easily disprovable ones.
And then we are going
to run test time error.
So again, I haven't told
you what is test-time RL,
but I'm going to get there.
OK day one, we are there.
Tuesday at 1:00 PM, we
received the problem.
And P1 is an algebra.
P2 is a number theory and
P3 is a combinatorics.
And P1, P2 actually requires
an answer to be guessed.
And so we ask our experts to
manually formalize the problem,
then Gemini to guess
and second guess,
and then we get AlphaProof to
try to disprove all those answer
candidates.
And so we have already
very good signs
is that AlphaProof is able
to disprove 99% basically
of guesses for those two
problems in a matter of minutes.
And so this is a
really good sign,
because we've
observed in the past
that when AlphaProof
understands the problem,
it's going to be
able to disprove
a lot of false contexts.
But for problems that it
doesn't understand at all,
it wouldn't be able to
disprove much at all.
And so that's a really
good sign for day one.
On day two, we receive again,
at 1:00 PM the problems.
We knew actually
that P4 and P5 had
to be geometry and
combinatorics because there
is a rule that the easy
and medium problems--
all categories have to appear
in easy and medium problems.
But we are pretty
happy to see that P6
was algebra functional equation,
because we knew that also
AlphaProof was particularly
strong in functional equation
problems.
That said, P6 is in
the hard category.
And it's the hardest problem.
So even if it's a good
category for AlphaProof,
nothing is guaranteed at all.
And it turns out
that, AlphaGeometry
is able to solve the geometry
problem, I believe in seconds.
So really, really powerful.
It gets there.
So basically, they came
in, they run their thing
for a few seconds and
then it was done so then.
The P5 combinatorics
was actually very tricky
and our human experts failed
to formalize that problem
on the day.
And the P6 algebra,
it also requires
answers to be determined.
And Gemini generated
a bunch of answers.
And when we-- AlphaProof
try to disprove it,
it could only disprove
7% of guesses.
And so it doesn't have zero
traction on the problem,
but it doesn't have probably as
good an understanding as on P1
and P2.
All right.
So day 3, Thursday, AlphaProof
hasn't proved anything yet,
but we had a way
to track progress.
And so we observe on the
day 1 problems that P1--
AlphaProof had actually
solved half of the problem.
And so actually in
that proof, there
are at least two ways to
split that problem in two.
You'd case on the fact that
something is either even or odd
or that it's rational
or irrational.
And so AlphaProof had come up
with these ideas of splitting
this problem into 2 by itself.
And in, for instance,
in the even odd case,
it had proved the
even case and hadn't
finished proving the odd case.
It wasn't able to
prove the odd case yet.
In P2, when we look at it,
AlphaProof had arguably
solved the whole problem.
And so I don't know if
you know, but in the IMO,
there is a whole section where
after the competition is--
after the students have
submitted their answers,
the team captains can argue
with the judging committee that
actually like this student has
done this much and so therefore,
they deserve that much points.
And so if we had
followed that process,
we believe that with
whatever AlphaProof had,
we may be able to argue
for the whole problem.
So let's say, 6 out
of 7 points there.
And then on P3, the
combinatorics problem,
AlphaProof had hadn't
made any progress.
On the day two
problem, as I said,
Alpha Geometry hadalready
solved in seconds that problem.
So 7 out of 7 points.
The P5 combinatorics,
we had made no progress.
I think by that time, we
had a formalization of it.
But what was really cool is
that actually on P6 AlphaProof
had made progress and had proved
a particular case that we now
know is worth two
out of 7 points.
So probably on Thursday,
it had actually
made quite a bit of progress
on all the problems.
And we may have already
had like about 18 points.
Now, Friday we
received this email.
There is the name of my
colleague, Rishi, that
actually sent by AlphaProof.
And Alpha Proof is
sending an email
each time it solves one
of the IMO problems.
It says I have discovered a
truly marvelous proof of IMO
2024 P6.
But this email is
too short to contain.
And of course, it's a
joke and the whole proof
is there in the email.
And so when we see
that, we are extremely
excited because we know we
have P2, AlphaGeometry has P4.
We're making progress on P1.
And we have seen that it looks
like we have solved the hardest
problem,
P6.
So extremely excited.
I run to my colleague's
desk, Oliver Nash,
who is one of our Lean experts.
And so we basically copy-paste
that proof into official Lean,
and it sinks a little bit and
says yeah, all good proofed.
And so I run back to my desk.
I don't think too much.
I just forward that message
to Demis and Sergey.
So it's like Demis
Hassabis and Sergey Brin.
And I wanted to share
that for two things.
One, I think it shows you
the trust I have in Lean.
If I didn't trust
Lean, I would probably
wouldn't have sent
that email seconds
after getting confirmation from
Lean that this was all good.
And the second thing
I thought a little bit
after that is like oh,
was this a stupid email?
But I think actually we
are in a company where
it's cool to do this.
And Demis and Sergey
were following
a little bit what was happening
during this competition.
So yeah.
A little bit later in
the day, actually, we
receive another mail and
it's a full proof of P2.
So now there is
nothing to argue about.
Perfect proof solved AlphaProof,
and a little bit later
in the day, actually,
on that same day we also
received a full proof of P1.
So in conclusion, final results.
P1, P2, and P6 were fully
solved by AlphaProof,
and P4 was fully solved
by AlphaGeometry.
And we actually try
to keep running over
the weekend in the hope of
getting one point on P3,
because actually the agent
made some progress on it,
but it turned out that it was
not enough for a partial point.
So we reached the score
of a silver medalist
and missed the gold
threshold by one point.
Of course, I just want to
reiterate that we definitely
use more time and
more compute than was
available to the
human participant.
I want to come back a little
bit on this P6 problem,
because it turned out that it
was arguably one of the hardest
problems in the last
years at the IMO.
Only five out of 609
of the participants
solved this problem fully.
And it's the top-six
people of every country
who comes in and only five in
total solve the problem fully.
And Sir Timothy Gowers, who is
Fields medalist and IMO gold
medalist as well,
he said that he
actually spent a couple
of hours on this problem
and did not solve it.
And I find the fact that
the program can come up
with a somewhat complicated
construction like this very
impressive.
So in no way am I saying that
we are close to Tim Gowers math
abilities.
And he may not have spent
these two hours really trying
to solve this,
and these things--
these are-- you need to
practice to solve these things.
And so in no way am
I saying that we are
close to Fields Medal level.
But I think we all
interpreted this
as a really, really
encouraging sign for the future
to be able to do something
really non-trivial.
And let me conclude
this IMO part with some
of the challenges we observed.
The first is the
gaps in Mathlib.
And so the most blatant
one is geometry, actually.
If AlphaGeometry
was not there, you
may have required us to
actually completely write
that part in Mathlib so that we
could do the geometry problems,
or we may have decided not even
to try the geometry problem.
And also, I want to
say that even in P1,
we observed that actually
there were some gaps in Mathlib
that we suffered from.
And so in one of
the proofs where
you have to prove that it's
either rational or irrational,
Alpha Proof hadproved
the rational part
and was struggling on
the irrational part.
And so this is not
definitive, but, in fact,
we observed that the
natural way to prove this
would be to use a certain
theorem that turned out
to not exist in Mathlib.
So this is not an excuse.
AlphaProof could
have conjectured
that theorem, proved it in line
and use it to finish that proof.
But it turned out that
problem was more difficult
than it needed to be.
Now, combinatorics problems
were also very difficult.
Just P5 was extremely
hard to formalize.
A lot of-- the necessary API to
represent those problems about
actually ironically about agents
environments and strategies is
not present in
Mathlib and that was--
made that problem very
hard to formalize.
And the reality is that even
when we had formalize it,
we did not manage to make
progress on P3 and P5.
So combinatorics were
difficult for AlphaGo.
And of course, we use
many orders of magnitude
more compute than
human contestants.
In some way.
I think, we actually
successfully landed on the moon.
I think that is actually
the important part.
And we will want to be more
efficient for the next trip.
All right.
So now let me go
into the methods.
And before we get there,
I want to remind you
that, when we're talking
about the methods,
there are two important aspects
we needed to think about.
One is where do the
problems come from
and how are we going
to have an agent that
learns to solve those problems?
So we trained several models.
One model is a formalized model.
So it takes as an
input a problem
described in natural language
in output a Lean formalization.
So this is based
on the idea that we
are going to lean onto
human-defined problems
instead of inventing
our own problems,
and we are going to
try to translate them
in Lean, because they all
exist in natural language,
but they don't exist in it.
So we're going to
try to do that--
trying to do that with
humans don't scale at all,
takes a long time.
And so instead, we want to
try to train a model that
can do this automatically.
That's the formalized model.
And now we also
have a proven model.
So the architecture of a proven
model is that it takes this--
if you remember in
my demonstration
before this yellow
box, the Tactic state,
the Lean state that tells
you, what do you know now?
What do you need to prove?
This is the thing we're
going to send as an input
to the proven model.
And then the proven model is
going to sample n continuation
for the proof.
This n-thing you might consider
potentially part of the proof--
an alternatives.
And then you take
this proven model
and you put it in
the AlphaZero search.
So you're going to search over
actions which are basically
one line in the proof.
Each time you add one
line in the proof,
you send that to Lean.
And Lean tells you,
oh, what do I know now?
What do I need to prove now?
And that's basically
how the search works.
If you know a little bit about
AlphaZero and MCTS like search,
they try to exploit what
the networks tell you--
the neural networks tell you.
They exploit the high-prior
and high-value paths.
But it has a mechanism also
to explore low-visited paths.
So, for instance, that's how
Move 37 in AlphaGo is discovered
is because it might
have a low prior,
it might not be considered
the right move by the network.
But it was still going to
try to visit it in case,
it might be an interesting move.
So now let me put this thing
together in the pipeline.
Step 1, we do auto
formalization.
So we train a formalization
model and auto formalize
human creative problems.
So this is really the
answer to the question,
where the problems come from
around human mathematics.
And here I want to highlight
a few advantages of using
formalization of the problem.
First is that when you send
a problem to Lean and Lean
says this is a valid
syntax, it means
that your question makes sense.
And it's not something
that doesn't make sense.
So it's either true or false.
You're generating something
that is either true or false.
OK, the problems might
not be interesting.
They might be trivially
true or trivially false.
But they are either
true or false.
And so one way to
see this is you
have the human
problem in the middle
And you try to generate
Lean variants of it.
If your model is
really good, then you
will do the perfect translation.
But maybe also it
will generate problems
that look like that problem.
And so when we have this
formalization model,
the way we use it
is that we were
able to gather about a
million informal problems.
So there is a lot
of problems to train
for the IMO, about
a million of them.
We pass them through
our formalized model
and we generate roughly
for every problem described
in natural language, we
generated roughly 100
possible translation for it.
And now we've just
created a huge database
of formal problems.
Now, we need to have--
we need to train the prover
to be good at proving.
And so that's why
you don't really
want to be completely in
the AlphaZero philosophy,
where you really
start from scratch.
Here, you want to
be pragmatic and you
want to start with
something that
is already can do a few things.
So you take a pretrained model.
In our case, it was
pretrained on a lot of code.
And then the next step is you're
going to train the approval
model supervisor Mathlib.
The Mathlib has about 100,000
definitions, 200,000 theorems,
300,000 lines of proof.
And basically, you are really
going to do supervised.
So, you are going to
place yourself inside
of a human proof.
You're going to look at what
is the mean state there.
Then you're going to look
at what the human said
was the next step in the
proof, and you're going
to train the model towards it.
So in some sense, very similar
to regular pretraining but you
get much more
information from it.
And so when you've done
that, your proven model
has learned a really good
prior over the actions to take.
And unfortunately,
Mathlib is about,
I don't know, but especially
if you want to do the IMO,
Mathlib doesn't contain
much IMO problems.
It's all about research math.
And so if you take
that proven model
and you try to apply it on the
IMO, you get around 0% of rate
on the end.
I'm not going to say 0%.
I actually am not sure,
but really close to 0%.
And so that's why
you start to have
to discover new knowledge about
how to solve those IMO problems.
And so that's where you enter
the next stage of the AlphaZero
reinforcement learning stage.
And so you are going to
train the proven model by RL.
And the recipe is very simple.
It's RL recipe.
And for each form
of problem, you
are going to generate experience
or either proving or disproving
that problem by
searching over steps.
And once you've come up with
what you think is a proof,
you're going to use Lean
to verify the proofs.
Lean is going to say,
this is not a proof.
This is a proof.
And for the things
that are proof,
you are going to reinforce your
proven network on those proofs.
And so what happens is
that, at the very beginning,
the proof model is able to prove
the very-- the easiest problems,
really, really easy
problems is going
to learn from that experience
and climb the next rung
on the ladder that leads all
the way to IMO strengths, right?
It's going to be able
to then solve a few more
problems a bit harder.
And by learning from
those, it will go and get
better and better and better
and all the way to the IMO
And.
So for this stage, we decided
to do a really the AlphaZero
pipeline, because what we wanted
to see is that, of course,
we want to solve the IMO,
but we want to do it in a way
that we think will generalize
way beyond the IMO.
So our real goal is to do
real mathematics is not
to stop at the IMO.
So we want to have a method
that is not tuned to the IMO,
and we want to have a method
that can discover new knowledge.
And so all these proving
strategies for the IMO,
this is completely discovered
by the model by itself.
So that's step 3.
And then final step is this
thing called test-time RL.
And so to give you a bit of
context, as I alluded before,
even for Po-Shen Loh, the USA
coach, or Tim Gowers or Terry
Tao, the problems at
the IMO are not obvious.
So even if you have a Fields
Medal level neural network
of mathematical intuition, you
cannot really solve those IMO
problems instantly.
But then-- even for them,
it takes hours to solve.
And why is that?
It's because, those problems
have been designed this way
and you really want to learn
something about those problems.
So it's almost a real
scientific experiment.
You first need to
think of experiments.
In this case, it's like
what could be true,
what could be false?
And then you need to
run the experiments
try to proves or
disproves those problems
and learn from this
experience to learn
about that particular problem.
And the way we did it
is that, AlphaProof
is going to generate variants of
the problem we are caring about.
So in this case, we have
these six problems at the IMO.
These are the problems
we care about.
Can we generate variants
of those problems
and basically then run RL
exactly as in the previous step
to try to discover knowledge,
especially about those problems?
So I'll try to illustrate this
in some hyperplane, where you
have the agent and the problem.
And so yeah, try to
imagine this a little bit.
So on the bottom left, basically
you have a bubble of problems
that the agent can
already solve easily.
And so it's a
generous checkpoint.
Every little black dots here
represent kind of a problem
that the agent already
knows how to do.
And then very far
on the top right,
you have this very hard
problem that you want to solve.
So imagine maybe it's the
P6 problem [INAUDIBLE].
And so as I described, the
first thing we did was we
generated variants
of that thing.
So we basically
explored that problem
into many, many variants.
And if you are
doing this well, you
may hope that it will generate
one variant that is actually
already solvable by the agent.
And so you solve that one
and you learn from that proof
exactly like before.
And you learned a little
bit about that problem.
And then you repeat
that process.
You repeat that process.
You learn about that
problem until you reach--
you reach that problem
and you can solve it.
And so that's how actually
P1 and P2 and P6, all of them
require test-time
RL to be solved.
So I want to finish this
section with some challenges
for AlphaProof.
So we inherit some challenges
from formal mathematics.
As I said, most of human
data is in natural language.
But we started to
have a good handle
on how to translate
that human data so
that we could learn about it.
And so there's still
a big challenge,
especially as we move forward.
But maybe we have some handle
on maybe something that is a bit
harder is that we cannot easily
learn and work on areas that are
not supported by Mathlib.
So for instance, like
in the geometric case,
where if you have
nothing about it, right,
you can't even express
the geometric problems
that humans have come up with.
And so that's a real
challenge to think about.
And so this could
be solved if you
start to understand how to do
creative building of new objects
and theories.
You understand interestingness
and beauty in mathematics.
But this is definitely a really
cool challenge for future work.
Cool.
So what's next for AlphaProof?
And as I said, from
the very beginning,
actually, of the
AlphaProof project,
the idea was to try to see if
we could learn about mathematics
and potentially go
beyond human mathematics.
The IMO was really,
really cool milestone
that I think was extremely
correlated with that goal.
But that's not where
we want to stop.
So obviously, what
we want to do is
we want to broaden to the
entire mathematical landscape.
We don't want to be stuck
as high-school mathematics.
And we want in the future
to be able to contribute
to the frontiers of
research math and going back
to the understanding that the
Greeks got 2,500 years ago
of the importance of proof.
It would be fantastic if we
could democratize-- democratize
this idea of a proof and
share that with every thinker
from an elite mathematician
to any other person.
And so can we have AlphaProof as
a useful tool for every thinker?
And I want to conclude by saying
that the big ideas they are
really important, but equally
important, if not more,
is the people who
are doing this with
and the mindset that
everyone has on the team.
And I was pleasantly surprised
to hear that, in mathematics as
well, you need to be
really optimistic,
otherwise you will never
be able to prove anything.
I think this is also true
in AI and machine learning.
It needs to be absurdly
optimistic to be
able to achieve absurd goals.
And really, individually
this was almost impossible.
But we had this belief
that together it
was impossible to fail.
And so these were
the team members
that contributed to
this amazing project.
And yeah, let me conclude that
and thank you for listening.